<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A famous speech of King Henry the eighth, made in the Parliament House the 24. of December, in the 37. yeare of his Majesties reigne. Anno Dom. 1545. Tending to charity and concord, and therefore necessary for men of these times.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86208</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E199_41</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9898</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873629</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873629</idno>
            <idno type="VID">157536</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86208)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 157536)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 35:E199[41])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A famous speech of King Henry the eighth, made in the Parliament House the 24. of December, in the 37. yeare of his Majesties reigne. Anno Dom. 1545. Tending to charity and concord, and therefore necessary for men of these times.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII)</author>
                  <author>Henry VIII, King of England, 1491-1547.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Speeches, addresses, etc., English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1509-1547 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:157536:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
            <p>A famous SPEECH OF King Henry the eighth, MADE In the Parliament Houſe the 24. of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember, in the 37. yeare of his Majeſties Reigne. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1545.</p>
            <p>Tending to Charity and Concord, and therefore neceſſary for men of theſe times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the yeare, 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:157536:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:157536:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
            <head>
               <hi>A Famous</hi> SPEECH OF KING HENRY THE EIGHT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough my Chauncellor for the time being, hath before this time uſed very eloquent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſubſtantially to make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to ſuch Orations as have beene ſet forth in this high Court of Parliament, yet is hee not ſo able to open and ſet forth my minde and meaning, and the ſecrets of my heart in ſo plain and ample manner as I my ſelfe am and can doe.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I taking upon me to anſwer your elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Oration Mr. Speaker, ſay that where you in the name of our welbeloved Commons, hath both praiſed and extolled me for the notable qualities that you have conceived to be in me, I moſt hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thanke you all that you have put me in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of my duty, which is to endeavour my ſelfe to obtaine and get ſuch excellent qualities, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary vertues as a Prince or Governour ſhould or
<pb facs="tcp:157536:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
ought to have, of which gifts I recognize my ſelfe both bare and barren, but of ſuch ſmall qualities as God hath endowed mee withall, I render to his goodneſſe my moſt humble thankes, intending with all my wit and diligence to get and acquire to me ſuch Noble Vertues and Princely Qualities as you have alledged to be incorporate in my perſon.</p>
            <p>Theſe thanks for your loving admonition and good counſell firſt remembred, I eftſoones thanke you again, becauſe that you conſidering Our great charges (not for Our pleaſure, but for your defence, not for Our gain, but to Our great coſt) which We have lately ſuſtained, as well in defence of Our and your enemies, as for the conqueſt of that fortreſſe which was to this Realme moſt diſpleſant and noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and ſhall be by Gods grace hereafter to our Nation moſt profitable and pleaſant, have freely of your owne mindes granted to Us a certaine Subſidy here in an Act ſpecified, which verily wee take in good part, regarding more your kindneſſe then the profit thereof, as he that ſetteth more by your loving hearts, then by your ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>Beſides this hearty kindneſſe I can not a little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice when I conſider the perfect truſt &amp; ſure confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence which you have put in me, as men having un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted hope, and unfained beliefe in my good do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and juſt proceedings for you, without any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire or requeſt, have committed to mine order and diſpoſition all Chauntreyes, Colledges, Hoſpitalls, and other places ſpecified in a certaine Act, firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly truſting that I will order them to the glory of
<pb facs="tcp:157536:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
God, and the profit of the Common wealth.</p>
            <p>Surely if I contrary to your expectation, ſhould ſuffer the Miniſters of the Church to decay, or lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (which is ſo great a jewell) to bee miniſhed, or poore and miſerable people to be unrelieved, you might ſay that I being put in ſo ſpeciall a truſt as I am in this caſe, were no truſty friend to you, nor charitable man to any poore Chriſtian, neither a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of the Publicke-wealth, nor yet one that feared God, to whom account muſt bee rendred of all our doings. Doubt not I pray you, but your expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall be ſerved more godly and goodly then you will wiſh or deſire as hereafter you ſhall plainly perceive.</p>
            <p>Now ſithence I finde ſuch kindneſſe on your part otward me, I cannot chuſe but love and favour you, affirming that no Prince in the world more favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his ſubjects then I doe you, nor no Subjects or Commons more love and obey their Soveraigne Lord then I perceive you doe me, for whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence my treaſure ſhal not be hidden, nor if neceſſity require my perſon ſhall not be unadventured: yet although I with you, and you with me, bee in this perfect love and concord, this friendly amity can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not continue, except you my Lords Temporall, and you my Lords Spirituall, and you my loving Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſtudy and take paines to amend one thing which ſurely is amiſſe, and far out of order, to the which I moſt heartily require you, which is, that charity and concord is not amongſt you, but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and diſſention beareth rule in every place.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:157536:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in the Corinthians and in the 13. Chaper, Charity is gentle, Charity is not envious, Charity is not proud, and ſo forth in the ſaid Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: Behold then what charity and love is amongſt you when one calleth the other Heretick and Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt, and hee calleth him againe Papiſt, Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite and Phariſee, bee theſe tokens of charity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you? Are theſe ſignes of fraternall love between you? No, no, I aſſure you that this lack of charity among your ſelves, will be the hindrance and aſſwaging of the fervent love betweene us, as I ſaid before, except this wound be ſalved and cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made whole.</p>
            <p>I muſt needs judge the fault and occaſion of this diſcord to bee partly by negligence of you the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Preachers of the ſpirituality, for if I know a man which liveth in adultery, I muſt judge him a lecherous and carnall perſon, if I ſee a man boaſt and brag himſelfe, I cannot but deem him a proud man. I ſee here daily that you of the Clergy preach one againſt another, teach one contrary to another, inveigh one againſt another without cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity or diſcretion. Some bee ſo ſtiffe in their old <hi>Mumpſimus,</hi> others be ſo buſie and envious in their new <hi>Sumpſimus.</hi> Thus all men almoſt be in variety and diſcord, and few or none preach truly &amp; ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the word of God according as they ought to do.</p>
            <p>Shall I judge you charitable perſons doing thus? No, no, I cannot doe ſo; alas how can the poore ſoules live in concord, when you Preachers ſow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them in your Sermons debate and diſcord?
<pb facs="tcp:157536:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->
Of you they looke for light, and you bring them to darkeneſſe. Amend theſe crimes I exhort you, and ſet forth Gods word both by true preaching and good example giving, or elſe I whom God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed his Vicar and high Miniſter here, will ſee theſe diviſions extinct, and theſe enormities cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected according to my very duty, or elſe I am an unprofitable ſervant, and an untrue Officer.</p>
            <p>Although I ſay the Spirituall men be in ſome fault, that charity is not kept amongſt you, yet you of the Temporality be not cleane and unſpotted of malice and envy, for you raile on Biſhops, ſpeake ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly of Prieſts, and rebuke and taunt Preachers, both contray to good order, and Chriſtian fraterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: If you know ſurely that a Biſhop or Preacher, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth or teacheth perverſe doctrine, come and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it to ſome of our Councell, or to us, to whom is committed by God the high authority to reforme and order ſuch cauſes and behaviours, and be not judges your ſelves of your owne phantaſticall opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and vaine expoſitions, for in ſuch high cauſes ye may lightly erre.</p>
            <p>And although you bee permitted to read holy Scripture, and to have the word of God in your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tongue, you muſt underſtand that it is licenced you ſo to doe, onely to enforme your owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and to inſtruct your children and family, and not to diſpute and make Scripture a railing and taunting ſtocke againſt Prieſts and Preachers (as many light perſons doe) I am very ſory to know and heare how unreverently that moſt pretious je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well
<pb facs="tcp:157536:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->
the word of God is diſputed, rimed, ſung and jangled in every Alehouſe and Taverne, contrary to the true meaning and Doctrine of the ſame.</p>
            <p>And yet I am even as much ſorry that the readers of the ſame follow it in doing ſo faintly and coldly; for of this I am ſure, that charity was never ſo faint amongſt you, and vertuous and godly living was never leſſe uſed, nor God himſelfe amongſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians was never leſſe reverenced, honoured and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Therefore as I ſaid before, be in charity one with another, like brother and brother; love, dread and feare God, (to the which I as your ſupreame head and Soveraigne Lord, exhort and require you) and then I doubt not but that love and league that I ſpake of in the beginning ſhall never be diſſolved or broken between us.</p>
            <p>And to the making of Lawes which bee now made and concluded, I exhort you the makers to be as diligent in putting them in execution, as you were in making and furthering of the ſame, or elſe your labour ſhall be in vaine, and your Common-wealth nothing relieved. Now to your Petition concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our Royall Aſſent to be given to ſuch Acts as have paſſed both Houſes: They ſhall be read open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that ye may hear them. Then were they openly read, and to many his Grace aſſented, and diver he aſſented not unto. This the Kings Oration was to his Subjects there preſent ſuch comfort, that the like joy could not bee unto them in this world. And thus the Acts made as the manner is, and his Aſſent given, his Grace roſe and departed.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
